<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo speeches in Parliament of the right honourable William, Lord Vicount Say and Seale Mr. of his Majesties Court of Wards and Liveries, and one of his Majesties most honourable Privie Councell, the first upon the bill against bishops power in civill affaires and courts of judicature. The other a declaration of himself touching the liturgie, and separation.</title>
            <author>Saye and Sele, William Fiennes, Viscount, 1582-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895937</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153538</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153538)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2370:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo speeches in Parliament of the right honourable William, Lord Vicount Say and Seale Mr. of his Majesties Court of Wards and Liveries, and one of his Majesties most honourable Privie Councell, the first upon the bill against bishops power in civill affaires and courts of judicature. The other a declaration of himself touching the liturgie, and separation.</title>
                  <author>Saye and Sele, William Fiennes, Viscount, 1582-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Vnderhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition has pagination [2], 17, [1] p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153538:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SPEECHES IN PARLIAMENT OF THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> LORD Vicount SAY and SEALE, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of his Majeſties Court of Wards and Liveries, and one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privie Councell, The firſt upon the Bill againſt Biſhops power in civill affaires and Courts of Judicature. The other a Declaration of himſelf touching the Liturgie, and ſeparation.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Vnderhill.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:153538:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153538:2"/>
            <head>A Speech of the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable WILLIAM, Lord Vicount <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seale,</hi> one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable privie Councell, ſpoken in Parliament, upon the Bill againſt the Biſhops.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not need to begin as high as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in anſwer to what hath bin drawne downe from thence by a Biſhop con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this queſtion,<note place="margin">The Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne.</hi>
               </note> for that which is pertinent to it will onely be what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes Biſhops as they are miniſters of the Goſpell, what was before (being of another nature) can give no rule to this. The queſtion that will lye before your Lordſhips in paſſing of this bill is not whether Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie (I meane this Hierarchicall Epiſcopacy which the world now holds forth to us) ſhall be taken away Roote and branch, but whether thoſe exuberant and ſuperfluous branches, which draw away the ſap from the tree, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it from the right and proper uſe whereby it becomes unfruitfull, ſhall be cut off, as they uſe to plucke up ſuckers from the Roote. The queſtion will be no more but this, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops ſhall be reduced to what they were in their firſt advancement over the Presbyters (which although it were but a humane device for the Remedy of Schiſme, yet were they in thoſe times leaſt offenſive) or continue ſtill with the addition of ſuch things, as their owne ambition, and the ignorance and ſuperſtition of ſucceeding times did adde thereunto, and which are now continued for ſeverall politicke ends, things heterogeneall and inconſiſtent with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153538:3"/>their calling and function, as they are miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and thereupon ſuch, as ever have been, and ever will be, hurtfull to themſelves, and make them hurtfull to others, in the times and places where they are continued. And theſe things alone this bill takes away, that is their offices and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Courts of Judicature, and their imployments by Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of office in civill affaires: I ſhall inſiſt upon this, to ſhew firſt how theſe things hurt themſelves, and ſecondly, how they have made, and ever will make them hurtfull to others; They themſelves are hurt thereby in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in their credits; In their conſciences, by ſeeking or admitting things which are inconſiſtent with that function and office which God hath ſet them apart unto. They are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated unto a ſpeciall worke, and men muſt take heed how they miſ-imploy things dedicated and ſet apart to the ſervice of God; They are called to preach the Goſpell, and ſet apart to the worke of the miniſtery, and the Apoſtle ſaith, who is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for theſe things, ſhewing that this requireth the whole man, and all is too little, therefore for them to ſeeke, or take other offices which ſhal require and tye them to imploy their time and ſtudies in the affaires of this world, wil draw a guilt upon them, as being inconſiſtent with that which God doth call them and ſet them apart unto. In this reſpect our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath expreſly prohibited it, telling his Apoſtles that they ſhould not Lord it over their Brethren, nor exerciſe Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over them, as was uſed in civill governments among the Heathen: They were called gracious Lords, and exerciſed Juriſdiction as Lords over others, and ſure they might lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe ſo: but to the Miniſters of the Goſpel our Saviour gives this Rule, it ſhall not be ſo done by you; If ye ſtrive for great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he ſhall be the greateſt, that is the greateſt ſervant to the reſt; therefore in another place he ſaith, Hee that putteth his hand to the Plow and looketh backe to the things of this world is not fit for the kingdom of God, that is the preaching of the Goſpel, as it is uſually called. To be thus withdrawne by intangling themſelves with the affaires of this life by the neceſsity and duty of an Office received from men, from the diſcharge of that Office which God hath called them unto,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153538:3"/>brings a woe upon them; Woe unto me, ſaith the Apoſtle, if I preach not the Goſpel, what doth he meane? If I preach not once a quarter, or once a yeare in the Kings Chappell? No, he himſelf interpreted it; Preach the Word, be inſtant, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, rebuke, exhort, or inſtruct, with all long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and doctrine: he that hath an office, muſt attend upon his office, eſpecially this of the miniſtery. The practice of the Apoſtles is anſwerable to the direction, and doctrine of our Saviour. There never was, nor will be, men of ſo great abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and gifts as they were indued withall, yet they thought it ſo inconſiſtent with their Callings to take places of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in civill matters, and ſecular affaires and imployments upon them, that they would not admit of the care and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that a buſineſſe farre more agreeable to their Callings, then theſe, would caſt upon them, and they give the reaſon of it, in the ſixth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> It is not reaſon that we ſhould leave the word of God and ſerve Tables. And again, when they had appointed them to chooſe men fit for that buſineſſe, they inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute an office rather for taking care of the poore, then they by it would be diſtracted from the principall worke of their Calling, and then ſhew how they ought to imploy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; But we (ſaid they) will give our ſelves continually to prayer, and to the miniſtry of the Word; Did the Apoſtles, men of extraordinary giſts, thinke it unreaſonable for them to be hindred from giving themſelves continually to preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word and Prayer, by taking care for the tables of the poore Widowes, and can the Biſhops now thinke it reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or lawfull for them to contend for ſitting at Councell Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to governe States, to turne States-men in ſtead of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to ſit in the higheſt Courts of Judicature, and to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in making lawes for civill polities and government? If they ſhall be thought fit to ſit in ſuch places, and will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſuch imployments, they muſt not fit there as ignorant men, but muſt be knowing men in buſineſſes of State, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Rules and lawes of government, and therby both their time and ſtudies muſt be neceſſarily diverted from that which God hath called them unto; And this ſure is much more unlawfull for them to admit of, then that which the Apoſtles rejected as a diſtraction unreaſonable for them to be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153538:4"/>by. The doctrine of the Apoſtles is agreeable to their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice herein, for <hi>Paul</hi> when hee inſtructeth <hi>Timothy</hi> for the work of the miniſtery preſſeth this argument from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a good Souldier, no man that warreth intangleth himſelfe with the affaires of the world: So that I conclude, That which by the commandement of our Saviour, by the practice and doctrine of the Apoſtles, and I may add by the Canons of ancient Councels, grounded thereupon, is prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Miniſters of the Goſpell, and ſhewed to be ſuch a diſtraction unto them from their Callings and function, as wil bring a woe upon them, and is not reaſonable for them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of; If they ſhall notwithſtanding intangle themſelves withall, and enter into, it will bring a guilt upon their ſoules, and hurt them in reſpect of their conſciences.</p>
            <p>In the next place it doth blemiſh them, and ſtrike them in their credit, ſo farre from truth is that poſition which they deſire to poſſeſſe the world withall, that unleſſe they may have theſe outward trappings of worldly pomp added to the Miniſtry, that Calling will grow into contempt, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed. The truth is, theſe things caſt contempt upon them in the eyes of men. They gaine them cap and courteſie, but they have caſt them out of the conſciences of men; and the reaſon is this, every thing is eſteemed as it is eminent in its owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per excellencie; the eye in ſeeing, not in hearing; the eare in hearing, not in ſpeaking; The one would be rather monſtrous then comely, the other is ever acceptable being proper; ſo is it with them, their proper excellency is ſpirituall, the deniall of the world with the pomp and preferments, and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof, this they ſhould teach and practiſe, but when they contrary hereunto ſeeke after a worldly excellency like the great men of the world, and to rule and dominere as they doe contrary to our Saviours precept, <hi>Vos autem non ſic,</hi> but it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you, in ſteid of honor &amp; eſteem they have brought upon themſelves in the hearts of the people that contempt and <hi>odium</hi> which they now lye under, and that juſtly and neceſſarily, becauſe the world ſeeth that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a worldly excellency, and run after it, and contend for it, before their owne, which being ſpirituall is farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and which being proper to the Miniſtry is that alone
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153538:4"/>which will put a value and eſteem upon them that are of that Calling. As theſe things hurt themſelves in their conſciences and credit, ſo have they, and, if they be continued, ſtill will make them hurtfull to others; The reaſon is, becauſe they break out of their owne orbe, and move irregularly; there is a curſe upon their leaving of their owne place. The heavenly bodies while they keep within their own ſpheres give light and comfort to the world, But if they ſhould break out, and fall from their regular and proper motions, they would ſet the world on fire: ſo have theſe done while they kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the work of their miniſtry alone, and gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to prayer, and the miniſtry of the Word, according to the example of the Apoſtles, the world received the greateſt benefits by them, they were the light, and life thereof; But when their ambition caſt them down like ſtarres from heaven to earth, and they did grow once to be advanced above their brethren, I doe appeale to all who have beene verſed in the ancient Eccleſiaſticall ſtories, or moderne Hiſtories, whether they have not been the common incendiaries of the Chriſtian world, never ceaſing from contention one with another about the precedency of their Sees, and Churches, Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one another, drawing Princes to be parties with them, and thereby caſting them into bloody warres. Their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and intermedling with ſecular affaires and State buſineſſe, hath bin the cauſe of ſhedding more Chriſtian blood then any thing elſe in the Chriſtian world, and this no man can deny that is verſed in Hiſtory; But we need not go out of our own Kingdome for examples of their inſolency and cruelty; when they had a dependency upon the Pope, and any footing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by out of the Land, there were never any that carried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſo much ſcorn and inſolency towards the Princes of this Kingdom, as they have done.<note place="margin">Lincolne.</note> Two of them the Biſhop that laſt ſpake hath named, but inſtances of many more may be given whereof there would be no end. Although the Pope be caſt off, yet now there is another inconvenience no leſſe prejudiciall to the Kingdome by their ſitting in this Houſe, and that is, they have ſuch an abſolute dependency upon the King, that they ſit not here as freemen. That which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to freedome, is to be void of hopes and feares; Hee that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153538:5"/>can lay downe theſe is a free-man, and will be ſo in this houſe; But for the Biſhops as the caſe ſtands with them, it is not likely they will lay aſide their hopes, greater Biſhopricks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill in expectancy: and for their fears they cannot lay them downe, ſince their places and ſeats in Parliament are not inveſted in them by blood, and ſo hereditary, but by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexation of a Barony to their office, and depending upon that office, ſo that they may be deprived of their office, and thereby of their places, at the Kings pleaſure, they doe not ſo much as ſit here <hi>dum bene ſe geſſerint,</hi> as the Judges now by your Lordſhips petition to the King have their places granted them, but at will and pleaſure, and therefore as they were all excluded by <hi>Edw.</hi> the firſt as long as hee pleaſed, and Lawes made <hi>excluſo Clero,</hi> ſo may they be by any King at his pleaſure in like manner, they muſt needs therefore bee in an abſolute dependencie upon the Crowne, and thereby at devotion for their votes, which how prejudiciall it hath beene, and will be, to this houſe, I need not ſay.</p>
            <p>I have now ſhewed your Lordſhips how hurtfull to themſelves and others theſe things which the bill would take away have beene, I will only anſwer ſome Objections which I have met withall, and then crave your pardon for troubling you ſo long.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. It will be ſaid that they have beene very antient.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they are eſtabliſhed by law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it may be an infringement to the priviledges of the Houſe of Peeres, for the houſe of Commons to ſend up a Bill to take away ſome of their members.</p>
            <p>To theſe three objections the anſwer will be eaſie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the firſt, Antiquity is no good plea, for that which is by experience found to be hurtfull, the longer it hath done hurt the more cauſe there is now to remove it, that it may doe no more, beſides other irregularities are as antient which have bin thought fit to be redreſſed, and this is not ſo antient, but that it may truly be ſaid, <hi>Non fuit ſic ab initio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For being eſtabliſhed by Law, the law-makers have the ſame power, and the ſame charge, to alter old lawes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, as to make new that are neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153538:5"/>
3. For priviledge of the Houſe it can be no breach of it, for either eſtate may propoſe to other by way of bill what they conceive to be for publick good, and they have power reſpectively of accepting or refuſing.</p>
            <p>There are two other Objections which may ſeeme to have more force, but they wil receive ſatisfactory anſwers.</p>
            <p>The one is, that if they may remove Biſhops, they may as well next time remove Barons and Earles: for anſwer.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon is not the ſame, the one ſitting by an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour inveſted in their blood, and hereditary, which though it be in the King to grant alone, yet being once granted he cannot take away; the other ſitting by a Barony de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon an Office which may be taken away, for if they be deprived of their office they ſit not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their ſitting is not ſo eſſentiall, for Lawes have bin, and may be made, they being all excluded, but it can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſhewed, that ever there were Lawes made by the King, and them, the Lords and Earles excluded.</p>
            <p>The other objection is this, that this Bill alters the foundation of this houſe, and innovations which ſhake foundations are dangerous.</p>
            <p>I anſwer firſt, that if there ſhould be an error in the foundation, when it ſhall be found, and the maſter-builders be met together, they may, nay, they ought rather to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, then to ſuffer it to runne on ſtill, to the prejudice and danger of the whole ſtructure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, I ſay this is not fundamentall to this Houſe, for it hath ſtood without them, and done all that appertaines to the power thereof without them, yea, they being wholly excluded, and that which hath beene done for a time at the Kings pleaſure, may be done with as little danger for a longer time, and when it appears to be fit and for publick good, not onely may, but ought to be done altogether by the ſupreame Power.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153538:6"/>
            <head>A Speech of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable WILLIAM, Lord Vicount <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seale,</hi> one of his Majeſties moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable privie Councell, ſpoken in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, touching the <hi>Liturgie</hi> and <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have waited to find you free from greater buſineſſes, that I might crave leave to ſpeake of ſomething that concernes my ſelfe; And this I have the more deſired ſince my Lord of <hi>Canterburies</hi> laſt ſpeech, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his troubles, and bewailing the miſerie of his condition, and of the condition of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (for he would needs joyne them together, which I thinke he may as the cauſe and effect, for the miſeries of the Church have certainly riſen from him) hee inſiſted much upon this, That theſe troubles had befallen him through the malice of two parties, the Papiſts, and the Sectaries, and by thoſe hee ſaid the Church was greatly afflicted. How farre this man will extend this word Sectarie, and whom he will comprehend under it, I know not, but I have ſome cauſe to feare that I may lye under ſome miſapprehenſions in reſpect of matters of this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153538:6"/>nature, which how farre it concerneth him your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips will perceive by what I ſhall ſay. My Lord of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> a man of meane birth, bred up in a Colledge, (and that too frequently falls out to be in a faction,) whoſe narrow comprehensions extended it ſelfe no farther then to carry on a ſide in the Colledge, or canvas for a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors place in the Univerſitie, being ſuddenly advanced to higheſt places of government in Church and State, had not his heart inlarged, by the inlargement of his fortune, but ſtill the maintaining of his partie was that which fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all his thoughts, which he proſecuted with ſo much violence and inconſiderateneſſe, that he had not an eye to ſee the conſequences thereof to the Church and State, until hee had brought both into thoſe diſtractions, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and diſhonour, which we now find our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed withall; Yet to magnifie his moderation, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the breaking of the laſt Parliament hee told a Lord who ſitteth now in my ſight, that if he had beene a violent man, hee wanted no occaſion to ſhew it, for hee obſerved that my Lord <hi>Say</hi> never came to prayers, and added, that I was in his knowledge as great a Separatiſt as any was in <hi>England.</hi> My Lords, how farre hee hath ſpit this venome of his againſt me, I am not certaine; But I may well feare where it might doe me greateſt preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; I ſhall therefore intreat your Lordſhips favours and patience, that I may give you in theſe things which ſo neerely concerne me a true account of my ſelfe, which I ſhall doe with ingenuity and cleareneſſe, and ſo as that if I ſatisfie not all men, yet I hope I ſhall make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare I am not ſuch a one as this waſpiſh man was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make the world beleeve.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe that he chargeth upon me, it may be he was willing to have it thought that I would not joyne in prayer with your Lordſhips, but refuſed ſuch a communion, which is altogether falſe, for I ſhould moſt willingly joyne in prayer with you. And further I will adde, that I doe not thinke but ſome ſet formes of prayer,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153538:7"/>by ſome men, in ſome caſes, may be lawfully uſed; But this is that which I am not ſatisfied in, that a certaine number of men ſhould uſurpe an authority unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to frame certaine prayers and formes of divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and when that is done, under the name of the Church to injoyne them upon all perſons, in all times, and upon all occaſions to be uſed and none other: and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ground (which makes it the worſe) becauſe theſe come from the publike ſpirit of the Church (when the Biſhop or his Chaplaine ſhall frame them) and others proceed from the private ſpirit of this or that particular man.</p>
            <p>This injunction is an uſurpation of power over the Churches of Chriſt, and over the gifts and graces which Chriſt hath given unto men: which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles never exerciſed nor would aſſume, and yet they might much better have done it, and the ſame reaſons might then have beene alledged for it, that are now; This turnes ſuch formes, in ſtead of being directions, into ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
            <p>This ſets aſide the gifts and graces which Chriſt hath given, and thruſts out the exerciſe of them, to ſubſtitute in their places, and introduce a device of man. This injunction of ſuch formes upon all men, turnes that, which in the beginning neceſſity brought in for the helpe of inſufficiency, to be now the continuance and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of inſufficiencie, and a barre to the exerciſe of able and ſufficient gifts and graces: As if becauſe ſome men had need to make uſe of Crutches, all men ſhould bee prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the uſe of their legges, and injoyned to take up ſuch crutches as have beene prepared for thoſe who had no legges. This I confeſſe I am not ſatisfied in, yet I will further ſay thus much, here are with your Lordſhips ſome Biſhops, men of great parts, able to offer up this worſhip unto God, in the uſe of thoſe gifts which God hath endowed them with: and certainly they ought to ſerve him with the beſt of their abilities which they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153538:7"/>have received. Let them make uſe of their owne gifts, nay let them but profeſſe that they accompt not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound to uſe formes; nor to this forme they uſe, more then any other, but that it is free to them to conceive prayer, or to helpe themſelves by the uſe of any other forme they pleaſe aſwell as this preſcribed; And let them practiſe the ſame indifferently, that ſo it may be manifeſt the fault reſts in the perſon and not in the Service, in the negligence of him that may offer better if he will, not in the Injunction of that which is offered; And I will not refuſe to come to prayer: for I take the ſinne then to bee perſonall, and to reſide in the perſon officiating onely. I know not whether I expreſſe my ſelfe clearely to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in this or not, and it may ſeeme to be a nice ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity, give me leave therefore to indeavour to cleare it by an inſtance or two. In the time of the Law, when God appointed himſelfe to be worſhipped by offerings, and ſacrifices, the ſhadowes and types of thoſe truths which were to come; If a poore man that had not abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to bring a Bullocke, or a Ramme, or a Lambe, had brought a paire of Turtle Doves, or two young Pigeons, it would have beene in him an acceptable ſervice: But if a man of ability who had heards and flocks, ſhould out of negligence or covetouſneſſe, have ſpared the coſt of a Bullocke or a Ramme, and brought young Pigeons, his ſervice would have beene rejected, and himſelfe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: how much more would the ſervice have beene abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, if men ſhould have taken authority to have injoyned all to bring no other but Turtles or young Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, becauſe ſome were not able to doe more? In one caſe there might be a tollerable and lawfull uſe of that, which otherwiſe uſed (eſpecially if generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned) would have beene moſt unlawfull; God will be worſhipped with the fatte and the beſt of the inwards, the beſt of mens gifts and abilities, which he that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, or officiates in worſhipping, is to doe at his owne perill; And if it be left free unto him, the worſhip may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153538:8"/>be lawful to him that joyneth with him therein in it ſelfe, though performed in a negligent, and ſo in a ſinfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by the Miniſter, but if that manner bee injoyned, the Service it ſelfe is to be refuſed.</p>
            <p>Now in the time of the Goſpell God hath appointed the fooliſhneſſe of preaching (for ſo the world accompts it) to be the meanes whereby he will ſave thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; I conceive where there are no gifts inabling men to preach, there might bee a lawfull and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table uſe of reading of printed Sermons and Homilies, and in ſuch caſe they might very lawfully be heard; But if ſome men upon pretence to prevent extravagant preaching, ſhould take upon them to ſet forth a booke of publike or common Sermons fit for all times and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and ſhould injoyne Miniſters to conforme to thoſe, and uſe no other preaching at all, but the reading of theſe common Sermons or Homilies ſo deviſed for publike worſhip, this would make it utterly unlawful, and to be profeſſed againſt, as that which were the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of a humane device and injunction, in the place, and in ſtead of Gods ordinance, to the excluſion thereof, as the Phariſees, to eſtabliſh traditions of their owne, made void the commandements of God; let it bee conſidered what difference there can bee found betweene theſe, but onely this, Uſe and Cuſtome hath enured us to that of Prayer, not ſo in this of Preaching, and therefore the evill of it would eaſily appeare unto us if ſo injoyned.</p>
            <p>My Lords, let me preſume upon your patience ſo farre further, as to give me leave to ſpeake to the other impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation laid upon mee that I am a Separatiſt, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in <hi>England;</hi> and firſt I ſhall ſay of this word <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> as that learned man Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> of <hi>Eaton</hi> ſaith in a little Manuſcript of his which I have ſeene.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That where it may be rightly fixed and deſervedly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, it is certainly a great offence; But in common uſe now amongſt us it is no other then a Theologicall ſcar-crow, wherewith the potent and prevalent party uſeth to fright
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153538:8"/>and enforce thoſe who are not of their opinions to ſubſcribe to their dictates, without daring to question them, or bring them to any rule or examination either of Scripture or reaſon.</hi> And he obſerveth that this was too uſuall, even in ancient times as well as now.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay that there is a twofold ſeparation, one from the Univerſall or Catholike Church, which can no otherwiſe be made but by denying the faith, (for Faith and Love are the Requiſites unto that communion) the other is a ſeparation from this or that particular Church or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and that not in reſpect of difference with them in matter of faith or love, but in diſlike onely of ſuch corruptions in their externall worſhips and Liturgies as they doe admit of, and would injoyne upon others. This is a ſeparation not from their perſons as they are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but from their corruptions in matter of worſhip as they are therewith defiled; And this ſeparation every man that ſin keepe himſelfe pure from other mens ſins, and not ſin againſt his own conſcience, muſt make. And I will ingenuouſly confeſſe, that there are many things in many Churches or Congregations in <hi>England</hi> practiſed, and injoyned upon all to be practiſed and ſuffered, which I cannot practiſe, nor admit of; except I ſhould ſin againſt the light of my conſcience, untill I may out of the word of God be convinced of the lawfulneſſe of them, which hitherto I could never ſee ſufficient ground for. But my Lords, this is ſo farre from making me the greateſt Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſt in <hi>England,</hi> that it cannot argue me to be any at all; for my Lords, the Biſhops doe know that thoſe whom they uſually apply this terme unto are the Browniſts (as they call them by another name) and they know their tenents. The truth is, they differ with us in no fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall point of doctrine or ſaving truth, as I know.</p>
            <p>Their failing is in this, they hold that there is no true Church in <hi>England,</hi> no true Miniſtry, no true worſhip, which depend the one upon the other, they ſay all is Antichriſtian: here is their errour, they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153538:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſtinguiſh not betweene the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> or puritie of a true Church, and the <hi>eſſe</hi> or true being of it, though with many defects and groſſe corruptions, But conclude that becauſe ſuch things are wanting, which are indeed neceſſary to the well being of a true Church, and to be deſired, therefore there is none at all in being. I hold no ſuch opinion, but doe beleeve to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, That there are in <hi>England</hi> many true Churches, and a true Miniſtrie which I doe heare, and with which Churches I could joyne in communion were thoſe yokes of bondage which are laid upon them taken off, and thoſe corruptions removed which they doe (contrary as I thinke to their dutie) yeeld unto and admit of, and this I am ſure no ſeparatiſt in <hi>England</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that deſerveth that name. Therefore I hope your Lordſhips will in that reſpect let me ſtand right in your opinions. I ſhall now end with two requeſts.</p>
            <p>The one that your Lordſhips will pleaſe to pardon me for troubling you with ſo long a diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my ſelfe, I have not uſed it heretofore, and I am not like to offend againe in the ſame kind, it is but once, and your Lordſhips will conſider the occaſion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is humbly to intreat of you, that where you know there is one and the ſame God worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, one and the ſame faith imbraced, one and the ſame ſpirit working love, and cauſing an unblameable conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation without any offence to the State, in your brethren, that in all theſe concurre with you, you will not ſuffer them (for Ceremonies, and things to you indifferent, but not to them but burthens, which without offence to the State, or prejudice to the Churches, you may take off if you will) to be thruſt out of the Land, and cut off from their native Countrey, for if you thus ſhall wound the conſciences of your brethren, you will certainly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and ſinne againſt Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
